Abraham: Reporting cyber security
incidents is important in
maintaining the resilience of
public communications networks and
understanding the threat environment.
This enables companies and organisations
to strengthen their procedures and
put contingencies into place by
learning from other’s mistakes and
keeping up to date with trends.
Nicole: Staff need to be made aware
of the importance of cyber security
as they represent the business and
are often handling sensitive data.
Companies should make sure that all
staff are fully aware of issues and
what steps to take to maintain security
and what to do in case of a breach.
This training should be
delivered in a regular cadence
to ensure staff are always aware.
Abraham: A cyber security issue
usually means that something
has, or could have, put critical
systems or sensitive data at risk.
It can be anything from a malware attack
to an employee clicking on an email or
link from an untrusted source or losing
a storage device with sensitive data.
Nicole: It maybe something as small
as someone putting their password on a
'post it' by their computer or sharing
their log in details with others.
This might seem trivial and not a
'reportable offence' but it should be
addressed as it could lead to a potential
security risk with serious ramifications.
It may cause loss of trust
in a company and financial
loss with legal implications.
Abraham: There are many kinds of cyber
security incidents but those that
involve personal data breaches need
to be reported to the ICO [Information
Commissioner’s Office] within 72
hours of becoming aware of it.
If this affects an individual’s
rights and freedoms, then they
must also be told without delay.
Nicole: Where appropriate this will be
shared with the National Cyber security
centre [NCSC] and other law enforcement
and cyber crime agencies or regulators
such as NCA National Crime Agency,
the Financial Conduct Authority [FCA],
and the Payment Cards Industry [PCI].
Abraham: A key principle of the UK
General Data protection regulation
is that personal data is processed
securely and means that all systems
and services should have the correct
security to maintain confidentiality.
Nicole: In some more exceptional
cases, a cyber security incident
can result in actual physical harm.
This is especially true when it comes
to cyber-attacks on the healthcare
industry such as those affecting the NHS.
Also, with a wide range of new smart
appliances being developed especially
for the home including security
systems there is an opportunity
for hackers to take over personal
devices to surveil or gain control of.
The rise of IOT devices has created
new problems with technology being
used in more day-to-day things meaning
that there are new risks emerging.
Abraham: Vulnerability to cyber attack
should never be underestimated and hidden.
It is important to remember that
thinking that 'you won't be hacked
because nobody would want to', is not a
good defence and is sometimes referred
to as 'security through obscurity'.
To be able to maintain cyber security
at all levels it is important that
any issues, breaches, or attacks are
reported immediately to assess and
minimise any current or future damage.